so john kiriakou is an author
journalist
former cia officer specializing in the
middle east
he was the first u.s government official
to confirm in december 2007 that
waterboarding and other forms of torture
were used overseas to interrogate
prisoners
he's also the first ci officer to be
convicted for passing classified
information to a reporter
served a 30-month prison sentence for
that
you can hear his voice on 105.5 fm in
washington drive around listen to him
for four hours every day
his book the reluctant spy my secret
life in the cias
war on terror is a classic
get the audiobook print it's
phenomenal
uh we've asked him to talk about a few
points he witnessed within the cia
according to him his own words a great
deal of respect for palestinians
uh but we're asking is that respect
open or suppressed
um
he received many warnings regarding
covert israeli intelligence remove
maneuvers in the u.s so we're asking oh
really that sounds interesting arresting
what were those
and uh
he's been noted for refusing to
undertake the cia's enhanced
interrogation
training
waterboarding sleep deprivation that was
used on terror
suspects so
we'd like to know
what he makes about
reports that the cia justified and
adopted some techniques
based on israel so we've asked him a few
questions
including uh the good guy bad guy motif
that we're hearing once again and
whether the u.s could be sucked into a
war with iran so
it's just a probably 10 minutes worth of
this time but
[Laughter]
please welcome john kiriakou
thank you
good afternoon everybody thank you so
much
i'm very happy to be here i really am
this is a what a wonderful organization
a great event
it's not it's not a normal thing really
in washington that you're able to get
together with a group of like-minded
individuals and
and speak freely it's very nice i'd like
to do this in two parts if i may i want
to talk first a little bit about
my background at the cia and the way the
cia views human rights which is going to
seem odd i think to most of you and then
i'd like to answer um these specific
questions
uh
that we were just talking about first of
all i i joined the cia in
january of 1990. i was recruited
into the cia by my graduate school
advisor who was not really
a grad school advisor so much as he was
undercover as a grad school advisor
and he he recruited me into the cia
i spent the first
seven and a half years of my career
working
on and in the middle east almost
exclusively on iraq uh i worked for a
while
on kuwait i went into kuwait with the
marines on liberation day in 1991. very
exciting but it got
monotonous after a little while writing
papers that you knew nobody was going to
read
and we all thought we were so important
but nobody nobody paid any attention so
i decided to do something more exciting
more rewarding and i
got involved in counter-terrorism
operations as it turned out i was the
only person in the entire cia that spoke
both greek and arabic
and um
and so they sent me to uh to athens to
work on arab it's quaint now arab
communist uh
uh
terrorist groups do you remember the
popular front for the liberation of
palestine and
abu nidal and
they were all old men by the time i got
there it became nonsensical but anyway
it was a lot of fun and i got to sort of
learn the tradecraft and then i went
back to headquarters in 2000
after 10 years
mostly in the field and then september
11th uh hit
and september 11th changed
literally everything at the cia
when when bill clinton was elected
president in 1992 he was inaugurated of
course in january of 1993 the cia
underwent
something called a cull
we were ordered to go through the files
of literally every recruited asset we
had in the world
and if
those assets had any human rights
problems in their past we were ordered
to
cut ties with them to fire them
um
a lot of us laughed when we heard that
because can you imagine the cia saying
oh you were involved in human rights
abuse
five years ago we can't have anything to
do with you but by god they actually did
bill clinton was serious at the time
about human rights and we called a third
fully a third of the recruited assets
that the cia had around the world
that only lasted about seven years
and then george w bush became president
september 11th happened and everything
changed overnight
i'm going to go back to 1990
my very first day at the cia we had a
senior fbi agent come to talk to the new
hire class
and one of the things that he said has
stuck in my mind
all of these 32-plus years
we were talking about
counter-intelligence and the fbi's role
in counter-intelligence that is trying
to spot spies who are spying on us
whether they're moles which is unusual
or
intelligence officers of a foreign
country
well most embassies here in washington
have what are called declared officers
those are foreign intelligence officers
who are here and they are
formally known to the fbi and the cia as
intelligence officers right so they're
here to
exchange paper and liaise and
meet with their cia and fbi counterparts
and then go back to their embassies and
write a report and send it back to their
capitals
this fbi agent told us at the time that
the israeli embassy was
unusual now remember this is 32 years
ago so the information is very old but
just to give you an idea of what we were
looking at
the israeli embassy had two declared
officers one from shin bet and one from
mossad
and it had 187
undeclared officers
that the fbi had been able to identify
spread out all across america
in academia
in the defense contracting industry
uh we've all seen the americans right
the israelis do the same thing just like
we do the same thing
but we were told that very first day
that i was at the agency
that we have no
international friends
not really i mean you can argue now the
five eyes the british the the
australians new zealanders the canadians
not the israelis
the israelis were
a country a service that we
we had to be leery of in some cases we
had to fear
i thought that was probably an
overstatement at the time and after i
had been at the cia for three years i
decided i wanted to go overseas
there was a program that the state
department ran called the analyst
overseas program where they'll take cia
analysts and
transfer them to the state department so
you're a legitimate state department
foreign service officer and you go
overseas and you work for two years in
an embassy and then come back and you
transfer back to the cia so i thought
well do i want to go to jerusalem or do
i want to go somewhere else and i
decided to go to bahrain two of the
happiest years of my life
the guy that i sat next to for those
three years
he went to jerusalem along with his wife
now because they had been to israel
before the cia decided to declare them
as a courtesy and to say look we have
these two people this married couple
they're not spies they're analysts one
of them isn't even really an analyst
he's going to go to
graduate school
while his wife is doing the analysis
we just want you to know that they're
here as a courtesy
on assignment to the state department
what the israelis did over the next two
years was to carry out a campaign of
harassment and the reason i bring this
up is because it's quite common
i'm telling you this story because this
is just a normal
thing that happens
to americans especially to american cia
officers working and living in israel
they went to a party one night and they
came home it was party at the
ambassador's residence in tel aviv they
came home and all of their living room
furniture had been rearranged
all of it
so the message was
we can come into your house anytime we
want and there's nothing you can do
about it okay that's aggravating a
little bit but no damage done
the next time they went out they came
home and someone had defecated in all of
the toilets in their house
they had four bad four bedroom house
four bathroom house
and people had gone to the bathroom in
all four of the toilets and left it
unflushed
so another
not very nice message that we can harass
you anytime we want
the third time it happened
they came home and their dog was
yelping and laying on the floor of the
kitchen someone had cut its tail off
and then wrapped it in gauze and tape
and the third the fourth time it
happened to them they had
they had done their christmas shopping
they had a
a tree up in the uh
the living room and they had gone to the
ambassador's christmas party and when
they came back
all of the presents were gone all of
them
thousand dollars worth of christmas
presents
now this kind of thing happens all the
time and so
the ambassador has to go to the israelis
and say look cut it out
leave my people alone
and they say okay okay and then they'll
back off
for a little while and then they start
up again
i have a friend who was the senior cia
person
in country
and he went to work one day and the
ambassador said to him the craziest
thing happened last night he said i was
in the car and my driver was driving me
home
and i had a blowout and we had to pull
the car over to the side of the road and
it turned out that
two
tires on the right side had blown out
well they had been shot out
have any of you ever i mean all of us
have blown a tire have you ever blown
two at the same time just minding your
business driving down the highway
well sure enough these these two men
pulled up and they were so friendly and
so warm and
they got out and they helped us change
the one tire and then they stayed there
until the tow truck came to help us you
know tow the car to get the the second
tire
uh replaced
but then the ambassador's briefcase was
missing and in the briefcase were
personnel files because he was writing
end-of-year
performance evaluations
well that way
the friendly guys who stopped to help
change the tire can determine
who's getting a performance evaluation
from the ambassador and who's not
because the ones who aren't are cia
officers
right because it's the foreign service
people who are working for the
ambassador
so
we don't
do things like this to the israelis ever
we also don't spy on the israelis ever
because of the political pressure that
that would put the cia
under on capitol hill i made a little
note to myself to be sure to talk about
the dichotomy between the state
department and cia on one hand and the
white house and capitol hill on the
other hand
all the years that i worked at the cia
and being an animal an analyst working
on iraq and enemy country at the time
i was declared to
my god more foreign intelligence
services than i can even remember it was
dozens
dozens of them
i only spoke to the israelis once
in 15 years
that i was there
i had only been on the job about six
months
and i was told
by my boss
uh you're going to brief the israelis
this afternoon i said okay
and he said we don't meet with them here
in the building we can't trust them to
come into the building so we're going to
meet them out there's a special place
where we meet them
because they kept trying to bring bugs
into the building right
oh we'll give you this gift well the
gift weighs twice what it should because
it's full of batteries and a listening
device and you can't bring that in here
so um
i went to uh brief the israelis now
because i was the junior most analyst at
the time and it was like seven or eight
of us that were there
i was the last one to speak
and so we ran around the table and it
was the most sad person and the shin bet
person and they're writing down every
word that the analysts are saying
finally they came to me and because i
was not undercover i was an overt
employee at the time i used my real name
i said my name is john kiriakou and the
shin bed officer says to me spell it
so i spelled it for him and he looks up
and he says
you are
jewish
and i said i am not recruitable
and he stopped
and afterwards my boss said yeah you're
not gonna brief the israelis anymore
and so i didn't i never spoke to them
again now once i got overseas
again i was i was uh declared to so many
services and i was working in
counterterrorism and that's where you
really want there to be lots and lots of
cooperation
so
we would get calls uh you know from
this country in that country in the
other country and um
and we rarely said no well i can tell
you from firsthand experience when it
came time to work with the palestinians
i'm hard-pressed to think of
of a group of people who were more
committed to counter terrorism
uh to to peace i mean it was revelatory
for me
it was it was a group of people who
wanted to do the right thing they wanted
good relations they wanted progress for
their people
um they wanted to have a role in the
international community and it was a joy
to work with them
you know that was in that was between
1998 and 2000 and i thought wow that was
really great i wonder if that was an
anomaly and then i went to pakistan
in 2002
as the chief of counterterrorism
operations
and it got to the point where
the palestinians would would
come to the embassy and they would just
wave them in
come on in
because they belonged there we were
partners we were a team
that was the case at the cia and it was
also the case at the state department
now this note that i wrote to myself to
be sure to explain the dichotomy
is that it was exactly the opposite
at the white house and on capitol hill
because
we didn't have to answer to voters at
the cia
right
i don't care
what you know aipac says about me
if i'm at the cia i don't care i have a
job to do
and i was
i was bound to do it
the state department was the same way
the state department was often
criticized for something called
clientitis
you know you hear this a lot at the
state department that
people go to israel and they
and they serve for a couple of years and
then they come out
like really disliking israelis and
really loving palestinians
and then they say okay well then you
need to go to
berlin for a couple of years to cool off
beca we can't have all these arab lovers
in the
well it turns out that the whole state
department loves
loves arabs
it's just a completely different world
it's hard to describe and then you go to
the white house especially to the
national security council to work with
those people who who have these fancy
titles of senior assistant to the
president for such and such affairs and
assistant to the president and you say
this is the way things should be in our
policy on
you know
the levant or the maghreb or whatever it
is and they don't want to hear it
because you like arabs too much
well
with that said
um we all just
accepted it
and frankly
we all believed that we were right and
the white house was wrong capitol hill
forget it it's a lost cause
you know on capitol hill when we were
summoned to give briefings
we would get in the car with somebody
from the office of congressional affairs
and
they would always tell us before we
walked into the the
house or senate office buildings
remember say as little as you can
possibly get away with and try not to
answer the questions right
yeah that's what we would do
just don't answer the questions
just tell you can talk and talk and talk
and not really say anything and then
those senators and congressmen just get
up and walk away anyway so it never made
any difference
i want to answer these questions in the
little time that i have left
one is about chas freeman why in my view
was chas freeman not able to bring his
immense talent to office during the
obama administration i worked for chaz
freeman in riyadh when he was the
american ambassador to saudi arabia
and i i was blessed over the course of
my career with working with some
some of the most brilliant
diplomatic minds
anybody could encounter he was one of
them
he's a he's a giant
in diplomacy and an honest giant
and uh you know the the easy answer to
this question is aipac simply would not
allow him to assume this position this
is a guy that had been ambassador to
saudi arabia ambassador to china i think
he was director general of the of the
foreign service for a while he was the
chairman or deputy chairman of the
national intelligence council he's he's
published extensively he's a brilliant
author a historian
and barack obama names him
assistant secretary of defense for
international security and the israelis
said oh no you don't
he's pro-palestinian
and that fight lasted for more than a
year he waited for confirmation
and uh and finally on capitol hill
senators told the white house there's no
way we're going to confirm him
if the israelis say no he's not getting
the job and he didn't
he didn't now in different groups that
we have around town we've honored him in
other ways and his health is quite poor
right now
but but he was wronged by his country he
was wronged just because he believed in
in a level playing field
something that i got to see a lot of
here in washington over the years
i've been noted for refusing to
undertake the cia's enhanced
interrogation uh training
uh on uh terror suspects
uh yes i did i called it a torture
program i i had just returned from
pakistan
where i had led this raid that resulted
in the capture of abu zubaydah who's in
the news today because he lost his final
case at the supreme court yesterday
and
i was asked if i wanted to be trained in
the use of enhanced interrogation
techniques i'd never heard the term
before
and so i asked what it meant and my
colleagues said very excitedly we're
going to start getting rough with these
guys
and i said what does that mean and he
explained it to me
i said that sounds like a torture
program are you crazy
and he said no it's not a torture
program the president said we could do
it and justice the justice department
approved it
i said i don't know man that sounds like
a torture program i don't i don't think
i want to have anything to do with it i
said i had a moral and ethical problem
with it
um and so i'm i'm embarrassed to tell
you that of the 14 people who were asked
i was the only one who said no and these
were people that that i um no thank you
these were people that i i
traveled with and our wives were friends
and our kids played together and they
were normal people to me and it was a
shock that they could turn it off and
become monsters
when they had to murderers
in cold blood
this final question is did we learn this
from the israelis of course we did
we saw what the israelis were getting
away with
in these prisons that they had in the
west bank and in gaza
nobody raised any objection at all
and so we thought well if the israelis
can do it we can do it and the president
said we could and the justice department
said we could and so we did
now
of course we have to take the cia's word
for it they say they're not doing it
anymore
um we don't know
and my time is up so thank you so much
for this opportunity it was wonderful
thank you